Hello and welcome back to
another video with ItsDrDan.
And today we're gonna be looking at
energy in the first law of thermodynamics,
meaning that we're gonna be starting
to learn about how can be transferred
and some of the basic concepts.
So this is an introductory video just
to go over some fundamental concepts.
So where does this all start?
Well, thermochemistry is a study of
heat that is absorbed or released.
During a chemical or physical
change, meaning that if we have a
chemical reaction, that energy or
heat may be required to make it
happen or for it to be given off.
Or if we're trying to melt or boil or try
to condense an try to change the physical
state, an object heat may be required.
So we're gonna be trying to
look at a little bit of that.
And the big reason is because
these types of changes are
important to your everyday life.
They're all around you.
If you're just sitting right now in
your room watching this video on your
phone or on your laptop, you right now
are meta Metabolizing, the different
food that you've ingested recently.
If you're drinking water, it's going
through the different pathways.
Thousands upon thousands of
chemical reactions are occurring
every single millisecond.
Now, from there, energy is either being
free as probably Generated from trying to
break down that food is being converted.
Right.
If you had to drive to get to
school or to go to work or to do
anything, you burned fossil fuels.
If it's the winter time and you need
to heat your home using like, maybe if
you have like gas heat or if you have
electric, right, that is different
things that convert energy to help you
be able to use it or if you just be able
to use the basic necessities that you
find in your everyday life, right, to
make your cell phone or to make, uh, to
make your laptops or to make your home.
Produce all those things
required energy to do them right?
So it's all around you, and that's what
we're gonna be looking at in this video
and trying to understand the basic
concepts of how we can describe it,
how we're gonna see it in chemistry.
All right, let's take a look
at these different concepts.
All chemical reactions obey
the following two laws.
One is the law of the conservation of
mass, which we've covered in previous
videos, and then now the law of
conservation of energy, which is also
known as the first law of thermodynamics.
Now, what does that mean?
Well, essentially it tells you that the
total energy within a system is constant.
Meaning that if I have a system,
like a chemical reaction or let's say
even yourself as a system and you're
interacting with your surroundings
around it, well, essentially
energy is transferred, right?
So if you, uh, put your hand
on a cold surface, you'll feel
that surface in to get hot.
'cause your body heat
is being transferred.
Um, or if, let's say the vice versa.
If you put your hand on a hot pot,
you can feel that really quickly
by burning your hand, right?
That heat, that energy is
transferred, meaning that
essentially everything can be com.
All energies can be converted because
energy cannot be created or destroyed.
It is always converted and essentially is
something that links all of us together
because of this constant conversion.
Now energy can come in many different
forms, and that's what we're going to
be looking at and how we can actually
measure that and understand it.
So let's try to take a look at the
different types of energy and how
we can see first, it takes a lot of
work to get up there and it takes a
lot of energy to do so too, right?
So in chemistry, work is defined
as change in energy and it's
resulting from a process.
Now those processes can
occur in many different ways.
A lot of them, depending on the
type of energy, can really come
from all kinds of different sources.
So the first general idea of it is
thinking back to, let's say if you
had to take physical science in high
school or even just basic physics,
one thing that you learn about is
that total energy is essentially a
conversion between potential and kinetic.
Meaning that potential energy
is how much energy you have
stored within a system, right?
It's all about where is
like an object positioned.
So let's say if I had my pen up
here and I'm ready to drop it,
it has all the energy stored up
that it could be ready to drop.
Now, just by sitting here,
it's not doing anything.
But the second you drop it, that
energy is being converted, right?
So it's going from potential at its
highest point, and as it's going and
moving, moving, moving, moving, and
gaining energy as a result, right?
It's moving with a velocity.
That's when it's converted
to kinetic energy.
Potential kinetic as your total
energy in a, in a physics system
and how much it moves now.
What exactly does that
picture kind of look like?
Well, the way I like the picture is
thinking of the scene from the office
where Kevin is carrying all this chili
into the office and drops it all onto
the floor, will him carrying that pot
and holding it at its highest peak
that has all the potential energy in
the world to eventually be converted
to kinetic and spill over the floor.
And then once it's back on
the floor again, not moving.
Now it's back to potential.
It's inversion between two systems.
What other forms of energy
can you possibly see?
Well, we can also look at chemical energy.
I.
Meaning what is being stored within
bonds of molecules and compounds.
And this is where, as chemists is
something that we continuously seek
and try to understand, especially as
it applies to, let's say, uh, whether
it's burning something as I show
here, or even thinking of metabolism
and how we make new go, right?
Nutritionists are constantly trying to
figure out, okay, how much, how many
calories are there within this food item?
How much can it possibly have?
Can it actually help?
Do what you're trying to do, right?
Calories is a unit of energy.
So our jewels, we're constantly trying
to understand how much is stored.
Um, thermal energy is always
associated with how much movement is
there within a molecule or an atom.
Molecules move.
Electrons move.
They vibrate, they change.
The more they, the warmer they get, they
move even faster and faster and faster.
The pressure that they're, that
they're putting on an environment
is gonna change as a result.
Two.
This is something that's constantly
moving and flowing and it's associated
with essentially the entire world.
Now, things that we've learned about in
other videos in the past, energy from
radiant energy, so the electromagnetic
radiation, let's say from the sun or
from, um, waves that are essentially
giving their energy as those different
photons are being emitted, right?
That energy can be absorbed within
these chemical systems as well.
So it can come in many different ways.
Almost all chemical reactions
they can absorb or they either
absorb or they release heat.
Now, when this are release energy and then
the way that they, when they absorb or
release energy, it's in the form of heat.
So one thing that we're constantly
trying to measure in chemistry is that
is this transfer of energy between two
substances at different temperatures.
And what do we call this letter
that we represent this as we use the
letter Q to show, hey, this is heat.
The units for that are in joules.
Okay, so J-O-U-L-S.
And we use a letter J.
This is an S-I unit or an uh,
so this is something that we
could manipulate using prefixes.
So you can have millijoules,
millijoules, megajoules, all
these types of things as well.
And then we can also convert this
to the system of calories too.
Where one calorie is
equal to 4.184 joules.
So calories is more in the common
in the US and as an imperial unit
that we use to measure how much
energy there is, let's say in food.
Um, now some important things
to note about thinking of heat
and how it actually works.
Well, there's some little obvious
principles about is that heat
flows from hot to cold, right?
You can see that in your everyday life.
You know, if you're really,
really hot to during the day,
you want to try to cool off.
So what might you might do, you
might just find yourself standing
in front of the refrigerator on a
really hot day trying to cool off.
Um, heat is absorbed, meaning that this
q value that we're gonna define, uh,
through subsequent videos after this, if
it's a positive value, that means it's
being, that heat is being absorbed by
your system and that this is endothermic.
If heat is being released or coming off
of you, you are being exothermic, right?
So if you kind of hold your hand
close to your face, you can feel
the heat coming off of your body.
Those are exothermic reactions
and, and it work, essentially, it's
you're constantly releasing heat.
So the way that we can actually show
these and try to define how these
systems are, the first thing is
defining what the heck is a system.
Well, a system is anything where
the reaction is taking place.
So I drew these little boxes here to show,
okay, so I have a blue box and an AR and a
red box, and that is our chemical system.
Now, when it comes to, let's
say you as a system, the area
around you is your surroundings.
So you can feel, let's say,
heat giving off from you.
So like this is kind of
an example of you, right?
So you feel heat coming off of you.
Another example of this is like an
exothermic process, is if you have a heat
pack or a heat wrap and you feel that heat
coming off you, if you crack open the pack
and it starts getting really, really hot.
Well, these little orange lines here
showing that, okay, heat is being released
as, as a matter of fact, when this
happens, it'll be a negative U value.
When, let's say if you have an ice pack,
well, it's gonna be the opposite idea.
When the chemicals mixed together
in an ice pack, it's absorbing
heat from everything, making the
surrounding feel cold so the inside
is hot, the outside feels cold.
So it's all going in
subsorbing, that energy.
And we're gonna be looking into
that into future videos as well.
Now, one thing you might see here is that,
is that there's a letter H written and
something that's gonna be seen as well.
Well, this stands for the term enthalpy.
So what enthalpy is, is essentially,
um, it, there is a chemical form
or there is a formula for this.
It's a physics term.
Um, it represents heat, energy, and
it's related to pressure and volume.
But simplify this course.
What we are going to be doing is
that E or Q is equal to enthalpy.
Because we are dealing with
constant, we're assuming a constant
pressure and a constant volume
to simplify our calculations.
So essentially delta H is gonna
be equal to your energy, which
is, which is equivalent to your
reaction in this type of equations.
But we're simplifying it.
So if you see an H value, it
represents a form of energy.
Okay?
And this is what we're
gonna be using to describe.
Changes a phase, so like boiling and
freezing and all those kinds of things.
There's some final notes on this.
Is that one thing just to keep in mind,
energy cannot be created nor destroyed.
This was a crash course in Thermochemistry
because something that we use in the,
in the types of introductory chemistry,
but it's just to be understood that
heat Flows from one thing to another.
Um, so we don't create it.
We don't destroy it.
Thermal energy is not
the same thing as heat.
They sound the same, but they're not.
Thermal energy depends on the
kinetic energy of a molecule.
Meaning how much is it kind of dancing?
And Atoms will continuously move and
bounce, go from all over the place.
The colder they are, the more they stick
together, don't really, they the hotter
they are, the faster they move around.
Um, so one thing that we will see here
is that heat is all about how energy is
being transferred to going from hot, cold.
Thermal is movement, heat is.
Is essentially how energy is transferred.
So one thing is when we use temperature,
essentially it's the measure.
You remember from my temperature videos,
the measure of the average thermal energy
of an object, meaning that, let's say
if a molecule is very, very hot, it's
moving around, uh, all over the place.
So these molecules are kind of
bouncing into the balls, they're
moving all over the place.
This means that this has a
very high kinetic energy.
Versus this one over here, you see
that they're all stuck together.
They're frozen in place,
they're not moving.
So this is a low kinetic energy,
meaning that this is a low temperature
versus a high temperature on the left.
Okay, so this is gonna be a picture
that we're gonna be looking at quite
a bit, that as our temperature is
changing, the thermal energy changes, the
molecules move and behave differently.
Depending on that energy that's
being associated with it.
So this is just a general overview
of the terms and things that we're
going to be seeing in Thermochemistry.
Thank you so much for listening.
I hope that this video helped
you a little bit introduced to
the world of Thermochemistry.
As we dive further into it, you'll see a
lot more about how energy can be converted
and used in different applications.
So thank you so much for listening.
If you haven't yet, like
subscribe button and thank you
all so much for being around.
See y'all later.
Bye now.